Okay. And the meeting has started. I am
letting everyone into the meeting.
And so we'll give the usual minute or
two for everyone to come in from the
waiting room. Good morning everyone. Uh
we'll give everybody just another moment
or so to join us from the waiting room.
We have quite a few people today which
is always good to see. My name is
Dominic Zerllo and I am the director for
the New Mexico Department of Health um
medical cannabis and psilocybin center
and uh this is the medical psilocybin
advisory board meeting and I will turn
it on over to the chair Ian Dunn. Ian
the meeting is yours.
>> Good morning everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. I am the chair of the medical cell
advisory board. Thank you board members
for being here as well as any public
participants and the department of
course for all of the work you guys do
behind the scenes for this program. Um
thank you again. I will go ahead and
turn over to the introductions of the
rest of the board members and then we
can um oh yeah introduction of the rest
of the board members and then we can
move on to the agenda.
>> If someone from the department could
call role.
>> Sorry I was just about to do that again.
Thank you. Uh, so Brenda Burgard.
>> Oh, hello everyone. Uh, let me see if my
camera's on. Oh, it's not working. Um,
hello everyone. I'm Brenda Burgard. I am
a licensed practitioner counselor here
in New Mexico and I chair the education
and training for the psilocybin medical
program. Thank you very much and I'm
looking forward to this meeting today.
Uh,
>> Chris Paski.
Good morning every
>> Oh, Chris, your microphone muted itself.
>> That was me.
>> Good morning, everyone. Uh Chris Pisky.
I'm an advocate, a veteran, and a
natural medicine facilitator in
Colorado. And I'm just happy to be here.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Chris. Uh Dan Jennings.
Hi everyone. I'm Dan Jennings. I am the
chair of the research and continuous
improvement committee.
>> Thank you, Dan. Alana Dances.
>> Hi everyone. I'm Alana Dances. I am the
acting Medicaid director and chief
medical officer of the Medicaid program
within the healthcare authority.
>> Thank you, Alana. Uh Ian,
>> good morning everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. I'm a mental health advocate um
and patient that could benefit from this
program. So, I'm just very happy to be
able to support people with the
qualified conditions.
And yeah,
>> thank you Ian and Larry Leman.
>> Hi everybody. Good to see you all this
morning. I am um a professor at UNM. I'm
a researcher in psychedelic um studies
and therapies including psilocy. have
been member of the advisory board and
chair of the end of life committee.
Delighted to be here this morning.
>> Thank you, Larry. And it looks like
those are all of the committee members
that are present at this time.
>> Perfect. All righty. Um so we can go
ahead and move on to the agenda for
today.
See?
>> Oh, uh, Ian, the agenda today is really
just to review the documents.
>> It was the introductions, review the
documents on that.
>> Perfect. All righty. Um, so let's go
ahead and get started with the training
and education committee document. Um,
and I will allow Dominic or Brenda to
present that, whichever feels more
comfortable. I I've got them here. So,
I'll uh give me just a moment to share
screen and I will have them on up. So,
we do have two different documents. The
first which was reviewed um at um the
training and education advisory board or
committee meeting rather um back on the
12th.
Uh and so, pardon me everyone. I've just
got to get back to the beginning. I
[snorts] accidentally switched to a
little lower on it. Um, and what I will
be doing as we go through this is I'll
put it be doing it section by section
and I'll put each section into the chat
so people can read it as well as see it
on the screen. So, forgive me.
>> Thank you, Dominic. I'll just chime in
here every now and then uh because we
did have a lot of people commenting
yesterday and I just wanted to um make
sure that um there's some understanding
with um these documents because I think
a lot of people uh didn't quite
understand some of it. So I know Dominic
you'll fill in the the the blanks here
but I might chime in every now and then
and say something. I think one of the
main things I just wanted to just say
that uh um the bottlenecks of some of
these things that we really needed to
discuss and and Dominic I wanted to just
say you did a fabulous job at explaining
a lot of these but we might have to put
in some more um information in some of
the in some of this document just to
make it more clear for those that um
didn't quite understand what some of the
document was saying. So, I just wanted
to put that out there.
>> Absolutely. And thank you, Brenda. You
beat me to some of the comments I was
going to make before I start reviewing.
Um, and so in addition with that, just
to make sure that everybody knows, um,
the this is an outline of what we will
be looking at or potentially looking at
to include within the rules and moving
forward with the rule making. Part of
that part of the process is um as
everybody uh has experienced as we went
through the cultivation and laboratory
rule which I'm going to make an
announcement about in a moment. Um, but
what really happened is as we went
through that process once we have a
thumbs up here from from the board
essentially is we will be turning this
into the rule and then it will still go
through and continue to go through the
public process of rule hearings and
going through all of that. So again,
this is the outline of the the basics to
include on in. There may be some
specifics that get added in. We did have
some of that yesterday for example and
back on the 12th where we did add in
some items and so um and looking at
consideration for other potential
avenues and I'll touch on those as we
get to various points uh and have that
discussion because I want to make sure
that we're transparent about this and
that everybody understands the process
that we're going through. So with that
the big announcement that I did want to
make and we've actually have made it in
both the equity meeting and we had
discussed it very briefly yesterday but
the cultivation and laboratory rules
have actually promulgated they
promulgated on Tuesday and so those are
in effect what we will be doing is we
will be um and we are currently working
on the application system due to
contracting those contracts don't start
till July 1st so we anticipate having
the applications open. They are on will
be online. But we anticipate having
those open uh by the middle of uh July.
So just within a couple of weeks. But
with that in mind, if there's anyone who
is interested as far as the laboratory
and the cultivation aspect and to see
what is going to be required, they can
actually go to the regulations um and
actually review through those and see
exactly what is going to be required.
and those items will just be, you know,
the application packet itself will just
be submitted through an online system
that we'll publish. Um, and so we do
have that. So, we do have our first
rules and that is a great step forward.
Um, and we do have announcements that
are going out about it, but we wanted to
make sure to bring it up here in today's
meeting. So, um, uh, quite a big step.
[laughter]
So, uh, and Jorge, by the way, just put
that also in the chat. So, the link is
there in the chat for those rules. Yes,
Alana,
>> I just didn't know if we were going to
talk about this um comments about this.
Are we Is that coming next about
>> that'll be a part of it. I will bring
that up when we get to that section
which is coming up.
>> Okay.
>> Or do you mean the comments about the
cultivator rule or
>> No, no, no. I I was just thought we were
I if if you wanted about the permit
requirements that are on the screen.
>> Uh yes, that's what I'm about to
introduce and discuss those.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, uh and and I'm not necessarily
going to read verbatim as I mentioned.
I'm putting each section by section into
the chat and then we'll kind of go
through. So the requirements this starts
with as far as the requirements for the
different positions or the roles for the
different uh types of providers. The
first is the diagnostic clinician and
showing that they have to have a valid
uh current and valid license from a
recognized New Mexico licensing board
that allows the diagnosing of the the
qualifying condition. um and that they
have a New Mexico controlled substance
number and that they complete the NMDOH
training and educational continuing
educational requirements um and apply
and receive and maintain a valid permit
from the NMDOH medicals psilocybin
program as a diagnostic clinician and my
apologies um when we did this in the
committee it was pointed out we do have
in the requirements for continuing ad
there we had decided to do it as
two-year and we just neglected to edit
that out here So, I just took that out.
Now, um and um and just the one thing I
want to bring up here because we did and
have had individuals who have been uh
providing some comments saying that they
did not feel that the clinician needed
to have the controlled substance number
and we understand their position on it
and their discussion on it. Um and um
but as we have continued to look at it
from the department standpoint is while
this is a schedule one um uh drug at
this time because we are treating it in
other ways as a medication it still
needs to have that medical clearance to
be utilized in a therapy type practice.
So just like for example a social worker
in New Mexico can actually diagnose for
some of the behavioral health conditions
such as PTSD, they still cannot
prescribe the medication. They would
have to send them to a medical as in
like an MD or an NP nurse practitioner
in order to be able to get that
medication and to get that referral for
that medication or the prescription in
that case for that. And so in this case,
that's part of why the controlled
substance number is required here. We do
also understand part of their concern is
that many providers may feel that it
puts their licensing at jeopardy and
that there would be issues with regard
to it. Um, and what I would just like to
say is that has always been the same
situation with regard to cannabis. It
has been schedule one and we have had
thousands of providers who have referred
patients to the program. We are not
asking those providers to prescribe
psilocybin or in the previous case
cannabis. Um and there are the same
stigma and concern issues with regard to
um with regard to that uh that we had in
cannabis. And so we understand those
issues and we will be doing education
with providers in order to explain what
the situation is. It does not take that
liability away. There is always
liability but it does actually it does
help and we have as I mentioned we have
had thousands of providers who have um
referred patients and certified patients
for cannabis. We do not see this in as
any different. And in fact, the
landscape is very different now than it
was almost 20 years ago when we first
started cannabis. And when we first
started cannabis, it was quite a
struggle with regard to providers for
this same sort of provision. But again
the reason for this uh for the provision
is to ensure that there is that medical
um connect point for that and to ensure
that other aspects of it such as um
issues with regard to uh any potential
contraindications
for using psilocybin and other items
from a medical standpoint are looked at
are observed and are actually also
passed on to the practitioners at the
therapy. level.
Okay. And so, Larry,
>> yeah, [clears throat] thank you, Dom.
Thanks for the explanation. Um, I have
one question. It gets into how this is
going to work out with access and
finances. And Alana, you might want to
weigh on on this also. So, if I was
seeing somebody as the physician, as the
diagnostic clinician, um, is this going
to be like a billable visit or is this
going to turn into a um, a self-pay
visit for them? In other words, can I be
billing that I'm seeing them as
depression? Um going over uh confirming
that if they have a diagnosis of
depression, going over treatment options
that include psilocybin. Uh I'm curious
if that's been discussed and any
thoughts from anyone here on that.
>> Yeah, I can talk about that a little
bit. I think that I mean we do this for
medical aid and dying too and we do it
for cannabis. So in general if you're
Like if the purpose of the visit is to
diagnose someone with an an illness and
then the treatment of that is a separate
like they're not you're not actually
prescribing the treatment. You're saying
they have this and this could could
potentially these are things that they
may choose to proceed with that is not
part of it then that's a billable visit.
That's how we see it for those for those
three.
>> Thanks Lana. Do do I understand that
this visit would also include some level
of screening? I believe I read that. So
would that would that influ I think
we're we're not only saying that they
have depression but we're screening them
for depression as a diagnostic
clinician.
>> Yeah. I mean I think that's always been
billable screening.
>> Okay. Great. Great. Thanks. I think
>> kind of funky is the bill, you know, the
billing and then and this is the
treatment option and I'm prescribing
them this treatment then I think we're
getting stickier. Um, but I we've I mean
as far as like what we've done for for
other things that are not FDA approved
treatments is we just kind of write our
guidance that like
>> you're you're making a ref like a
reference or a referral or a suggestion.
You're not prescribing it from the
visit. Uh so I think that that piece is
is coverable.
>> Great. That's helpful. Any issues with
the diagnostic clinician being the
practitioner?
>> No.
>> Sorry. Go ahead, Elena.
>> No, but the the visit where you're doing
the treatment, that's the part that's
not billable,
>> right? So, that person would want to be
probably careful to the to clarify this
is a diagnostic and screening visit and
then um have a different visitor or
separate that. Okay. Super helpful.
Thank you. Yeah, sure. Um, can I just
ask one question here while I'm because
I had one I had went out of order. Um, I
just want to point something out. Not
something that I think needs to be
changed, but just making sure this is
what we mean. Um, a New Mexico
controlled substance number is not a
DEA. So, we're saying we want the
controlled substance number. We don't
require the DEA, which seems okay
because it's very, very expensive. But,
uh, just making sure that that's was
intentional.
Yes, it it actually it was um that is
the same requirement that we have with
regard to cannabis.
Okay. Um and uh we do have another
question here. Denali.
>> Hi everyone. Um, good morning. And I I
did want to just ask a couple of
questions and then um provide a little
context for where some of uh Healing
Advocacy Fund's concerns came from with
this category.
Um, well, I I think it it might be
helpful to zoom out a little bit. I'm
I'm really appreciative, Dominic, of
talking about the way that the law has
changed since the Linen uh and Airing
Compassionate Use Act. I I do think it's
important to call attention to how the
statute is different in this particular
way in part because of the things that
we've learned since cannabis. And so the
Lynn and Aaron Compassionate Use Act did
require that the practitioner the the
prescriber be someone who have a
prescribing
um be licensed in New Mexi New Mexico
Mexico New Mexico New Mexico New Mexico
New Mexico New Mexico New Mexico Mexico
to prescribe and administer drugs. And
that's something that the drafters of
the medical psilocybin act opted not to
to elect. Um, and I think we've lost
that. Um, but there I believe was a a
really important reason for that that
has to do with equity and access and a
lot of the things that we learned um in
medical cannabis about how how narrow it
is if we attach the entry point to a
very small license group. I I don't want
it to sound that, you know, we're we're
not focused on safety and and see the
role of highly highly qualified
physicians um within this program. I
think that that's incredibly appropriate
and and should have a place. I think the
problem is that we've conflated a safety
screening with the program entry. Um but
the statute unlike the linen air and
compassionate use act the statute says
specifically that the the medical
appropriateness of a candidate is based
solely on whether they have a diagnosis
with a qualifying condition. That
doesn't mean that everybody with a
qualifying condition is going to get
treatment. Of course we want to have
safety screenings. But in terms of the
entry point, in terms of what providers
in the state we are authorizing to
decide whether somebody enters or
doesn't, I think we've created. We're
setting ourselves up to create
um a a really small pool of providers
that's not consistent with the equity
and access that that those who fought so
hard for this bill um uh you know worked
on in design and and in advocacy. So, I
just I I understand and I see that this
is consistent with the medical cannabis
program, but the statute is not the same
and I'm I'm not [clears throat]
I I don't believe that this design is
supported by the statute because it goes
beyond the requirement of diagnosis. Um
and and that's not what the drafters,
you know, we didn't there are things
that are consistent with the linen and
compassionate usage act and where there
were opportunities to learn from things
that could provide better access. Um you
know, I'm really glad that the state
took that took that opportunity. But if
the department is is making rules that
are, you know, just just based on what
happened in compassionate use, I think I
I think there's there's going to be a
misalignment with the spirit of of the
the legislation itself, which um is
dramatically different in these ways.
Um I and I think just on the question of
billing the it's not it's not I um it's
not [clears throat]
of course diagnosing would be a um a
billable service. I think though what
what was a red flag to me when we go
down to training and education
requirements. It looks like we're also
asking this diagnostic clinician to do a
risk benefit analysis which again sounds
like something that's coming from the
liner and compassionate use act and and
is not a part of the medical psilocybin
act. um and and that you know when we're
asking a provider to to um in an
encounter say weigh the risk and
benefits of a schedule one substance I
think we're putting them in a really
difficult position billingwise about
that encounter. So um I might have more
to to add to this conversation as it
develops but those are the things for
now I'd like to to offer.
Thank you, Denali. Uh, and Chris Pesky.
All right. Thank you. Um,
I guess I have
some questions about how this diagnostic
clinician fits into the care team. Is
this a,
you know, after they provide entry to
the program, are they then still part of
the care team? Is this somebody that,
you know, the care team is going to need
to coordinate with? Um, and I guess I'll
start there, but I I do have some
follow-up questions, too.
>> Sure. Thank you, Chris. And yes,
actually, that is something and that
would actually be part of best practice.
And that's a part of actually what
Denali also touched on that it is very
important to have that um and and I'll
just call it medical clearance for
shortcut here but to have that medical
clearance and to ensure that that's
there. So we did actually look at other
potential methods or ways that could
happen. But if that if it were to happen
in a different way, it would for example
a patient would go to a therapist or a
clinical social worker, someone who's
otherwise going to be providing the
therapy and then have to refer them to
that that provider who's going to be
doing that medical clearance and that
medical check and then come back. So
part of the idea behind this is to have
a streamlined process and it actually
and in the opinion of our department
does not actually conflict at all with
the with the statute itself. Um it just
it helps to provide and ensure that
there is that medical safety in a more
streamlined process and it doesn't mean
that if a patient is talking with a
therapist or other provider doing
psilocybin that they can't still go
through that process. What we're simply
stating is prior to a patient going
through additional most likely
out-ofpocket expense, they should get
that diagnosis and that clearance first.
Um, and yes, they should continue to be
a part of that care team. That should be
that continual conversation between the
the different providers that are
involved in this.
So, I'm very concerned that this is
going to bottleneck access, especially
for veterans. And, you know, I go
through a private doctor. I get about
four minutes before his little buzzer
goes off and he's on to the next
patient. Um, and so I think all of this
is extremely concerning to me for access
issues. And I think Colorado and Oregon
have both shown this can be done
effectively and that you know any any
problematic
uh medical conditions
uh can be referred from their side
instead of requiring a medical screening
first.
Um thank you.
>> Thank you Chris. Dan
>> and thank you. Um, so my uh kind of I
probably to echo somebody else's
thoughts on this is like as being in a
very rural area here um I worry about
that there won't be enough of the
providers that number one would be uh in
this pool and then taking it down to
having a CS number and then it just even
being in my area. So uh one of the
things just as an example is like let's
say that I had you know terminal cancer
[clears throat]
and so I was uh diagnosed for end of
life. So would this mean that if my
practitioner, my oncologist or whatever
did not have was not part of this
program, then I would have to go find
somebody else to go through and
essentially rediagnose and to ensure
that I was a good candidate for this or
could that be done remotely? Or is the
provider, for example, if it's PTSD or
substance abuse or treatment resistant
depression, would they have to
essentially rediagnose the diagnosis
that I have?
Thank you, Dan. So, it it doesn't
actually invalidate previous diagnosis,
but it does make sure that the patient
does and is doesn't have any other
additional counterindications
uh that may have occurred since that
diagnosis. For example, someone could
have been diagnosed with PTSD 10 years
ago. Situations change, medications,
other things do change in that time. So
there still would need to be that
evaluation and that's really the purpose
of having this in place. Um the other
part as far as the rule yes the tele
medicine would be available that's not
that's something that is available uh
through that and the other part of it
and we discussed this somewhat yesterday
is part of what the the department is
looking at and needing to do and we did
the same was with regard to cannabis is
doing education with providers to be
able to help with that aspect to help to
ensure that it's going to be there. Will
it take time to build up? Everybody
keeps talking quite frankly as far as
there being a bottleneck. Regardless of
what the rules actually have, there will
be a bottleneck initially. This is not
going to be a situation where the rules
go into effect and we suddenly have a
program that has lots of providers, lots
of patients. It's going to take time to
build that infrastructure. And so this
allows us also to be able to build that
time. And as mentioned before, if we do
find that there are other issues or
other concerns, the regulations can
still be changed down the road. Uh we're
not looking at that this is the last
time we look at them. It's the final
time. Uh even after promulgation, we
know with any program in the first few
years, if changes are needed to be made,
those can be addressed and made. and
especially in order to be able to help
improve access and equity while still
maintaining the medical and safety
therapeutic aspects of the program. I
hope that helps.
Ian,
>> hi. Yes. Um, so I just wanted to answer
one of his questions that he had brought
up. So yes, online would be available
for that diagnostic clinician um, if
someone wanted to. So, um, imagine if it
was similar to the medical cannabis
program. My physician talked to me for
like 15 minutes. This person's job is
just to ensure physical safety, that
there's no bad drug interactions, that
there's no um condition that is going to
disqualify them or or put them at risk.
And then when it comes to like
psychological and all of that stuff and
actually dealing with the behavioral
science aspect, that's where we would
shift to that practitioner. We just
don't want to create a situation because
in Oregon and Colorado you don't have a
qualifying condition. There is no filter
out for um sick people and we are going
to be working with people that need end
of life care. And so we don't want to
put unnecessary burdens if we can't help
out these people and if we're not, you
know, doing a costbenefit analysis. And
I I bring that up not because it's from
the medical cannabis program, but
because it's from any prescription
medication. Any prescription medication
you take, we are supposed to run a
costbenefit analysis. See, is this
treating the right thing? Is this
treating the right person? Is this
treating the right ailment? Um, and so
on and so forth. So, I just wanted to
remind that this person, sure, it
theoretically could be a bottleneck, but
because all they're doing is looking at
your medical history, which was probably
filled out on a form before you arrived,
um, and medications and that kind of
thing, and then just making sure you're
physically safe, I think it's a good
idea to just kind of make sure because
we're already dealing with a vulnerable
group of people, which Oregon and
Colorado don't sift those out by law.
Um, we have to be extra careful with
these patients. Um, but thank you for
letting me speak.
Thank you, Ian. Alana.
>> Uh, yeah. Hi. Uh, so I mean, you know,
I've been a prescriber in the state for
like 15 years. Um, you know, I had many
I was a geriatric prescriber. I have
many many people who did cannabis and um
it it what I mean so how it works for
that which I is kind of what I'm
thinking for this and I think tell me if
I'm understanding it right like you need
a clinician to say this person has PTSD
this person does not have cardiac
disease and then they take that to
psilocybin and the psilocybin is the the
psilocybin program is the one who moves
it forward from there they don't have to
say the clinician doesn't have to say
like I'm referring this patient for the
psilocybin program or I think psilocybin
is the correct treatment for this
problem or or are we asking for them to
be making a referral because I think
that distinction as a prescriber if you
I mean I think any prescriber can say
yes they have this diagnosis no they
don't have these other diagnoses and so
um I I don't see like anyone who's
concerned about their their license
they're not necessarily they're they're
kind of decoupled from the psilocybin
program if you're just asking for that
that they're proving the diagnostic
criteria. Am I understanding that
correctly?
>> Essentially, Alana, yes. And it would be
a referral to the program and that's
where that change comes in and actually
helps to provide some of that additional
protection for those providers.
Yeah, I haven't really found it that
it's it's a particular
I I find this like I haven't been part
of this um subgroup and I find this to
be a really nice balance of protecting
safety on a brand new program that
hasn't rolled out. I mean when we look
at history when you move too fast you
hurt patients like scaling programs is
is where we hurt people. So doing it
thoughtfully, carefully protecting
people as we roll it out is very
important to me. And this seems to me to
really like strike that balance well. So
I'm I'm comfortable with it.
>> Thank you, Alana. And because we do have
a lot to go through, we just have two
hands that are up now. We'll take those
as comments at this point. Um and then
uh or I'm sorry, three hands. We'll take
those as comments at this point and then
going to move on. Regardless, we are
noting that there is, you know, concern
with regard to this. So, I want
everybody to realize we are hearing you.
Um, you know, and we do understand. Um,
but, uh, we do have a lot more that we
do need to go through. So, uh, if the
remaining folks can keep it a little
brief and then we'll move on. Um,
Denali.
>> Yeah. Uh, thank you all for the
opportunity to speak again. Um
just a couple of things as this
develops. I really agree with um the
with Alana your your point um about
scaling and protection and safety and um
I I think that those are really those
are really important things for us to
prioritize.
Um I'm a little bit worried that that's
not what we're doing. um instead of
recognizing
um that you know individual safety that
a safety determination is
patientspecific right I I there was just
an example of you know the 15 minutes
that you're probably going to spend with
someone I don't know that that's
adequate for this program um and and I'm
I it it feels like we are um in an
attempt to streamline I think that's the
word that the department used in this
time crunch
really what we've done is is implemented
a one-sizefits-all which says that every
patient who has a qualifying condition
um you know we're we're treating them uh
as if you know there there's going to be
a lot of complexities
um and I think especially for our end of
life care community it's going to be a
major barrier to access um and I just
want to correct something it sounds like
there's a perception that Colorado and
Oregon do not have um [clears throat]
safety protocols. They do and they have
safety protocols that work. Um however,
you know, they're ones that trust
providers and patients to make
individualized decisions and they happen
within the care model rather than at the
access point. And I think that that that
makes sense for safety. It's
individualized. Um, I'm not saying that
we don't have um, uh, contraindication
screenings. I'm saying I I don't know
that it makes sense to conflate that
with the entry point into the system
because we learn about people as they're
going through care. I mean, you know,
one of the things that I've been talking
about is, you know, other
pharmarmacological
substances or other um, other health
indications are not the only
contraindication. someone just might not
emotionally be ready for the kind of
experience that comes with an altered
state in psychedelics and that's
something that isn't going to be
screened um by someone who is at this
entry point. Um so I think we we need to
take a step back and think about when
we're when we make that assessment for
someone with a qualifying condition. Um
I I and I I just one more thing want to
um push back a little bit on this idea
that we can
push through the regulations as are go
through rulemaking and then fix them
later. Particularly when we create a
permit structure, we're creating if
diagnostic clinician is a permit group,
we've created a property interest for a
group of people who have a financial
interest now in providing that care. It
will be very difficult for the
department to if if you know we realize
a year from now you know what we're
right diagnostic clinician role doesn't
make sense we need the safety the safety
protocol to happen in a different point
we've already created a permit structure
and a property interest in that permit
structure for any provider that is holds
a permit from the department um and that
is a much more difficult thing to remedy
down the
Thank you, Denali. Chris, and then after
Chris, because uh that was the last hand
that was up at that time, we will be
moving forward.
So, first I I'd like to challenge the
notion that people are not receiving
treatment for illnesses in Colorado and
Oregon. PE veterans are going to Oregon
and Colorado to treat their PTSD and
depression and other uh issues. So,
and so are first responders. I see Paul
Walton's hand just shot up. Um
so to to say that that can't be done
safely under those structures is
incorrect. And um also I I think
the physical safety profile of
psilocybin is extremely high and we're
going to allow
you know I guess uh teleaalthbased
um
physical or you know background medical
background checks to be the access point
of this it it none of this adds up to me
honestly. So that's where where I'm at.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Chris.
Uh and so the next set of information uh
or the next section um is uh the
practitioner and I had put it in the
chat earlier but I will put it in again.
Um and again this is very similar and
the structure in structure at least is
very similar to it. Um the main
difference with regard to the
practitioner is that it's an individual
who is a licensed health care uh
professional um who um can provide the
integrative therapy.
Excuse me. Um, and essentially with
regard to this is they just have to have
uh a license from a uh a New Mexico
licensing board that allows for the
delivery of counseling, mental health
therapy or behavioral health therapy and
that it that is within their lensure
scope of practice. They of course will
need to complete um the training
requirements and then receive and
maintain their permit or certification
through the program.
Um and then facilitator is very similar
as far as that role. Um and again I'll
put that on in the chat. Um and so for
the facilitator, this is an individual
who is of course also completed the
appropriate training and of course uh
and requirements for it and will of
course then receive and maintain their
valid perimeter or certification from
the program. Are there any questions
regarding those two?
Okay. And now I'll go into the
educational requirements. So I will
start um with the uh the New Mexico
module and uh with the diagnostic
clinician. Pardon me everyone for a
moment while I am able to copy it on
over.
And because psilocybin especially right
now is a new um is a new field and
psychedelics is a new field within uh
practices right now. Um we do have the
New Mexico module. Now the New Mexico
module is something that will be created
by the department and that will be
offered free for all of the different
levels and roles. And so essentially
that will include um portions about the
medical psilocybin act, the why, the
how, the timeline, state versus federal
laws, risk, malpractice, etc. An
overview of psilocybin therapy in New
Mexico, patient flow, emergency response
plans, billing, coding, informed
consent, documentation, HIPPA, etc., and
cultural competency and sensitivity,
equity and access, history of New
Mexico, cultural considerations,
non-western traditional medical models
and cert which is spiritual,
existential, religious, theological
concerns and then of course there will
be as with anything whenever you do
trainings there does need to be a
demonstration of understanding of the
material. So there will be a test or an
exam of some sort. Um in addition with
that and and this is the part that's we
think is very important is because this
is new for many providers at all
different levels that there be um a
section and training with regard to
psilocybin pharmarmacinetics. So how
does this have interactions with other
medications or supplements? How it's
processed in the body dosing half-life?
Are there things for example with GLP1s
with the uh gastric emptying being
slowed and how that actually affects
then psilocybin itself? Um and then also
just overview of the responsibility for
the diagnosing clinician, their scope of
practice and their role within the care
team and the diagnosis itself and
education on diagnosing qualifying
conditions and medical clearance, the
benefit versus risk evaluation,
medication evaluating and monitoring.
Um, and then again, uh, some research
evaluation, just a a little bit about
what research there is and how people
can find it and looking it up, looking
it up. And then, of course, again, as
always, a test and demonstration of
their ability uh, or their understanding
of the material.
Uh, are there questions on this section
at this time? And Denali,
>> hi. Sorry, I was a little bit slow to
raise my hand. I had a I do have a
question on this one, but I wanted to
ask about the practitioner whether we're
going to consider certified peer support
workers or certified licensed alcoh drug
and alcohol counselors. Um, not licensed
drug and alcohol counselors. I think
that that is included, but I'm wondering
if those two license types um or
certification types will be included
>> uh for facilitators or if they have a an
actual
>> license. I'm asking for practitioners.
Yeah.
>> Right. So, if they act they do actually
have to have a license from a board that
shows that. So, if the different
licenses you're talking about are
licenses um and not certifications, then
yes, they could be. Um and you know
there are many different licenses
certifications that are out there which
is why we do limit it to those who have
it within their scope of practice
through their licensing board.
>> Okay. Um
>> and that is consistent with the uh with
the statute.
>> Okay. Um, I [clears throat]
sorry I'm I have a couple follow-up
questions that I'm really trying to I
know that there are a lot of things
around practicum too and I I want us to
get there. I do want to just point out
this is where in the education this risk
and uh benefit and risk evaluation. This
is the piece if we're asking a
diagnostic clinician to do this in the
encounter. This is the piece that I
think is going to make it vulnerable to
clawbacks from um insurance. Right? If
the if the encounter is for the purpose
of evaluating whether psilocybin is
appropriate, I think that that's going
to be a problem.
>> Thank you, Danelli.
And again, this is as far as education
so that providers are aware.
Okay. Uh, so the next set is the
practitioner. And I'm not going to copy
the, uh, New Mexico. Well, uh, sorry,
just for ease of and timing, I will go
ahead and copy that on over. Um, and,
um, uh, pardon me while I get down to
through all of it. This one is a little
bit longer.
And so these individuals for the at the
practitioner level would again go
through the New Mexico module. So that
is the same. Um and then uh they would
need to go through a basic module for
practitioners which would include uh a
basic life support certification. Um
which and there's been discussion about
does it need to include CPR rather than
just a VLS but then also first basic
first aid. Um and then for those
conducting sessions in natural
environments a wilderness first aid uh
or first responder certification. HIPPA
certification, overview of
responsibility for the practitioner, so
their scope of practice and therapeutic
responsibilities. And then again
research evaluation, finding research,
reading and reviewing. And then again a
test. Uh and then the next portion would
be psilocybin therapeutic model looking
at psilocybin phboinetics session and
dosing experiences reviewing education
of psychedelic therapy modalities
history of use models cultural
sensitivity and etc. Uh individual
treatment and group treatment modalities
and group dynamics and psychedelic
deescalation techniques and then
self-care and then again a test for that
module. Um and then the set and set and
setting module which is about the room,
the building and the therapy space,
preparation sessions, administration
day, for example, items like
transportation, the medical use,
[snorts] um and uh therapy modalities,
emergency preparedness, um and then
integrative sessions, uh post
administration, that's models of therapy
that are appropriate for psilocybin
treatment and traumainformed care. and
then medical monitoring during sessions
and what that would require or what
should be happening with regard to best
practices and psychedelic emergencies,
urgencies and safety protocols and then
again the test on it. Um the simulated
patient module would be required and
that simulated patient is so that before
the practitioners are doing their
practicum requirements which we'll get
into practicum in a little bit but that
they are actually going through
simulated or role- playinging type
experiences as far as per patients and
then the practicum requirements.
So uh with that um we do have a couple
of items in the chat and then Shane um
we did not stop responding to chat
questions. I'm just going through both.
So my apologies on it. As far as an
integration coach, the answer on that
would be the same as what Denali said.
If that is a lensure um through a
licensing board, then that could be if
it is not then it would not be on that.
Um and then Kate um yes for so the um
the diagnosing clinician does require a
little bit more information and um and
many and as far as for the New Mexico
module that everyone would go through um
that would be between 6 to 10 hours uh
we're trying to make that a little
streamlined but we also want to ensure
that that's going to have as uh the
information that would be appropriate on
that. Um, okay. And then we have Chris,
you've got your hand up. Go ahead.
>> Um, in regards to the wilderness first
aid or um, first responder training, I
think that the
u necessity of that should necessity of
that should be determined by access to
EMS instead of just being in a natural
environment, maybe more than an hour
away. But just because somebody's doing
a session in a natural environment, say,
you know, Bosski Farms,
um they they would have EMS
quickly available to them. Um and so
that that makes more sense to me than
requiring a two-day training for for
somebody who's got EMS available.
>> Thank you, Chris. I've added that on.
Uh, and Larry,
uh, yeah, two two things. One is, yeah,
I totally agree with Chris. We did a
whole community engagement process. Most
people actually would like to be in a
more natural environment, and many of
the places in Colorado is simply like it
can be a backyard or other sort of
things. I would I would try to change
that requirement to remote. um you know
as as far as when we're talking about
the um uh the stimulated patient module
and I think I'll wind up talking about
this more later when we talk about
practicum um I I think I think I think
we need to look at a way that in the
actual training where people can
work with um um healthy people other
trainees I don't think that people um
who are in training should immediately
be dropped into people with, you know,
treatment resistant depression and PTSD.
And I realize that may need some
revision to the actual bill. But, um,
that's how the training occurs in
Colorado. And I I think it's a it's a
much better way of people starting.
Start with a simulated patient module.
Start with a um a I don't want to say
well person. You maybe none of us are
well, but I mean someone who doesn't is
not a qualifying diagnosis and let our
trainees work with them.
Thank you, Larry. Um, and yes,
completely understand that. The thing to
remember is the bill does only require
the statute only only allows for the
treatment to occur with people who have
the qualifying condition, which is why
the simulated patient we think is very
important, especially in this case with
that. Um that would be something that
really as individuals are going through
their practicum really should be working
with the the therapists, the
practitioners that are doing and are are
uh leading that session or those
sessions to ensure that it's not
somebody who has severe illness or
anything else especially in those first
portions of the practicum. And so
that'll be something very that'll be
very important to outline in the best
practices portion which is not a part of
the regulation but uh for that um and so
that's just something that isn't
actually allowed uh within the statute
currently.
>> Thank you Dom. I guess I'm also
proposing that we consider the option in
the coming year to to allow that. I
think it may be important enough to um
they're looking at some type of a
additional bill might be might be
indicated.
>> Thank you, Larry. I appreciate it.
>> Uh and then um
uh in the chat, James has a a item about
personal bias in the patient bill of
rights. Um yes, James, that is a part of
some of the coverage with with all of
the roles.
Okay. And then Paul just put in about uh
adding in training for first responders
for harm reduction uh and looking at
bringing a program from Ohio um to New
Mexico for that. Um
okay.
Okay. Um and then with that we'll go on
over to the facilitator portion. Um, and
um, for the facilitator, it it actually
covers uh, pretty much the same items.
And so I'm not going to recopy
everything into it. Um, the difference
in it, and pardon me, I'm trying to find
where we have it here. Ah, here we go.
Is, um, that there is an additional set
that is actually about an overview of
therapeutic practices. um which is
essentially a 101 type overview. Um and
that that would be an additional aspect
that would need to be included on end
which also covers uh in in a little bit
more depth and would be more of like a
101 about therapeutic practices talking
about ethics, confidentiality and
therapeutic modalities.
Okay, Chris. Oh, I'm sorry. Uh Ian,
you're actually up first.
>> Hi. Yes. So, uh just to go with a
comment from James Brown. If we could
add to the overview of therapeutic
practices in the ethics, personal bias
and patient bill of rights.
>> Um
>> just to it falls within ethics. I know
just for clarity.
>> Thank you, Ian. Yeah, that that was part
of what I was saying is that is included
as a part of that. Again, this is
outlined. So yeah, that definitely is a
portion of that. So,
uh, Chris, you are next.
>> So, in regards to the therapeutic 101, I
don't necessarily think that's
appropriate for facilitators. Um, I
think it blurs the lines between therapy
and uh what it is a phil facilitator is
more likely to do, which is peer
support. Maybe peer support training
might be uh more appropriate.
Um,
>> like there's
>> Yes, go ahead.
>> If I may. So what that really is is it's
so they know what is happening in the
room, not that they're going to be
providing therapy. It's so that they
understand what is occurring with regard
to the therapeutic process, not actually
delivering it or anything else. So it's
more about them getting a little bit of
an understanding on it so that they're
able to to know what's occurring in the
room as things happen. But we can also
definitely add in the peer support. I
think that's a great idea and include
that on in as well.
Yeah, I I still I'm not sure I agree
with therapeutic 101 training. Like I'm
not a I'm not a therapist in training
because I'm a facilitator. You know, I
bring my own gifts to the room and and
me working with a therapist. it,
you know, we're we're learning from each
other all the time, but I'm not uh not
trying to emulate them in any way. Like
that's we have our own gifts that we
bring to the space,
>> right? No, no argument. This is again
more as a understanding.
Um, Alana.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm gonna Sorry to go out of
order a little bit, but I'm still a
little stuck on the role of the di diagn
diagnostic person. Um, and trying to
envision like so I have two questions
about it. One is do they need to be
enrolled in this program to be
considered a diagnostic clinician?
Yes, they would need to because they
would need to go through the training so
that they to ensure that they do
understand about psilocybin therapies.
>> Okay. And then do they need to say in
their note
recommends psilocybin?
>> Uh what they would do is they would do
an att testation that which is the same
that we do as far as cannabis. Uh that
they believe psilocybin could be more
beneficial than uh potentially harmful.
>> Okay. Okay. So, like for so for
cannabis, there's usually like an extra
form that says they have this diagnosis.
>> It'll all seeing it.
>> Yeah. It's all online. And for example,
that's a a simple at testation check box
>> online. Like they have to get into some
kind of portal to
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Thanks.
>> Yeah. All of the applications, all of
the processes will be online as far as
for that application portion, uh
certifying, all of that kind of aspect.
Okay.
Okay. The next set um is actually the uh
are the practicum requirements and
please give me just a moment to pull
those on up.
Okay. And so what we have uh here is uh
that the supervised practice will be 100
hours for facilitators and 120 for
practitioners. Um students would
participate in a minimum of 80 hours of
administration and same day therapy
sessions where they're provided the
opportunity to experience, observe, and
conduct with a minimum of 14 different
patients over eight different
administration and same minimum of eight
different administration and same day
therapy sessions. That would be broken
up into six individual and two group
sessions. and that the students will
participate in a minimum of 20 hours of
in-person preparation and
post-integration therapy sessions where
they're provided the opportunity to
experience observe or conduct where
lenture allows preparatory or
integrative therapy sessions. And again
here would include a minimum of six
different patients and one group at a
minimum. Um [snorts] and then
practitioners would need to complete an
additional 20 hours as a practitioner um
for the s the the purpose of being able
to supervise facilitators during the
in-person administration with at least a
minimum of two different patients during
an individual and one group. All of them
must take place in an approved it's in
an approved healing center or location
and that practicum supervisors and
students would of course have to follow
the rules and best practices that apply
to facilitation including but not
limiting to standards for
confidentiality and limits on scope of
practice.
and Brenda.
>> Uh yes, I just wanted to clarify on the
supervision uh role because that came up
yesterday. Um for supervisors usually
have to go through um testing and
training and uh uh to become a
supervisor for uh counselors. So would
this would be just um
uh just a supervisor uh for just
psilocybin. So it would just take you
were saying the 20 hours that they they
would have to take would be this would
uh initially I'm thinking this is just
going to be a separate program just for
psych for psilocybin uh supervisors the
20 hours
>> right so it would be so that they can
supervise those facilitators so they're
not supervising other licensed
individuals just so that they have the
understanding of if they're leading that
room especially in a group situation of
that they have experience in doing that
and their first time doing that isn't
just with with a new patient and with
them doing it. So it's essentially to
give them that practice to understand
how to work with the facilitators to
ensure that they also are all working
together as a team.
>> Yeah. I just wanted to make sure that we
were very clear about that because I
think um there was a little confusion
about that because
>> um for supervision
uh that is just a separate thing for
clinicians. So this too will also be in
its own thing this own yeah 20 hours. So
like for instance I can supervise but I
as a clinician right now but I need to
have a supervises to do that. So in
other words this is uh very separate
from what the the counseling board has.
So yeah I just wanted to make a very
clear distinction between that because
so many people are going well wait a
minute I'm a supervisor already as a
clinician. do I have to do this extra 20
hours to supervise for psychedelic
psychedelic forsilocybin um facility and
what you're saying is yes that's that 20
hours is separate okay just clarifying
>> yes thank you Brenda okay Chris
>> um can you scroll back up a little bit
Dominic I'm I'm curious about The Can
you describe what this same day therapy
sessions means exactly? Like often times
you
>> go ahead.
>> That's just the the day that
administration occurs and the the
therapy that's going through. So the
individual going through their journey.
>> Okay. So we're just talking about an
administration session. We're not saying
that you have to have therapy session
the same day as you're doing.
>> Correct. Correct. That's it's the Yeah.
And so part of the reason we're doing
that is actually goes to some of those
billing questions as far as well
administration itself and the time after
if that down the road we don't have an
answer on that yet but if down the road
some of that time might be able to be
build as far as for therapy aspects. Um
but again we don't have answers on that
just yet but that's what that just is.
So that's administration day. We just
want to ensure that they're doing this
on different administration days with
individuals.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you, Larry.
>> Thank you. Um I I have some kind of a
little bit of complex things to share.
one is I I think this is um a
beautifully in-depth training and it's
probably more than any of the um
psilocybin training programs that um
that are occurring across the countries
several of which which I've taken which
I think has some appropriateness here
because we're talking about working with
people that have um um that have
challenging conditions. Um I I do think
we need to look at the econ like how
this is going to work economically. Um,
you know, several people in the state
have gone up to Colorado and done a
practicum, which took three days. It
involved um, uh, just three trainees
there. The cheapest one is over $2,000.
Um, and so I I'm wondering about um, you
know, what are the expenses? I I think
it would be worth trying to model how we
think that's going to um that's going to
occur. Um the other is that um you know
there's the conditions that we're
talking about are very different from
each other. The end of life committee is
really feels that it's important that
there is training that's specific to um
to end of life um including ideally
sitting with people in your training.
And so um I think and again this is sort
of complex and probably not something
that's sorted out today but um I think
that you know that this training
involving multiple conditions and that
you know that particularly PTSD and end
of life I think have their own training
set and I I would recommend that before
anyone be approved to sit with people
with end of life and PTSD that they have
um training in those specific diagnosis.
>> Thank you Larry. And and that's actually
something that came up quite a bit in
the committee meetings and we really
were discussing that and about how do we
actually include that on in and part of
the reason why uh we don't have it in
the regulations and I'll explain what we
think could happen with it um is because
again from the cost standpoint we didn't
want to continue to inflate the cost and
we could actually say that with any of
the current conditions that there are
specific areas within um that really
require additional training for any
qualified condition and even potentially
any future qualifying condition. And so
what we really would be recommending and
looking at down the road is that the
training programs offer um endorsements
where they have additional training and
a different additional modules for
people to be able to do that. And then
you know for practitioners and
facilitators to go through that and then
as patients are looking for what we have
then we would be able to um those
providers would be able to say and we
have the endorsement for end of life for
PTSD so that [snorts] patients really
know this is someone who has that
additional specialty
sort of like a an additional board um uh
uh specialty.
Dom, should we be requiring we putting a
requirement though somewhere so that
that it's the state is making sure that
happens and not just the training
program or are you thinking that the
training program would not be approved
without having develop that pathway? Now
I think that it becomes more difficult
especially as we start having additional
conditions down the road added in
because then we would need to have those
endorsements for each one and that could
become very difficult for anybody uh
practitioner or provider. What if for
example you have a group a mixed group
of patients? Would that practitioner
then not be able to do that because they
don't have one endorsement for one of
the conditions? though and then creating
an issue and this points to what Dan was
talking about actually earlier in rural
and remote areas where that could really
create a problem for potential groups.
So, so that's why we're really looking
at it as far as encouraging that for uh
as far as like for future endorsements.
And by the way, that doesn't mean that's
not something that can't be added later.
Also, if it proves that we do need to
have that and require that
Thank you, Dub.
>> Thank you, Larry. Uh, and we have, uh,
Scott.
>> Yes. Hi, Scott Shannon here. I'm a
psychiatrist in Northern Colorado and
have been a psychedelic researcher for
the last eight years. I'm involved with
practicum training in Colorado.
uh practicum training in Colorado as a
distinguished educator and I have some
broad comments on uh the state regulated
programs in general and the context of
what's happening in the country. I think
one of the things we've seen in Oregon
and Colorado both is a marketkedly
reduced volume compared to what was
anticipated because of the cost of
training, the duration of training and
the cost of treatment. And these things
are all related. Um, and I think that
what we're seeing nationally is Compass
is proceeding with their phase three
study and application and they've gotten
a token from the federal government for
speedy review and it's likely we'll have
national psilocybin approval by this
time next year um from all readings that
we get and in that case compass is
likely to require some very limited
amount of uh training and
commercialization.
probably something on the order of 5 to
10 to 15 hours for providers and
probably much less than that for
prescribers. And I think it's just
important. We all have the desire to
keep safety and regulatory control on
these things, but I think what we've
seen both in Colorado and Oregon, and
now I'm concerned with New Mexico's
process as well, is it will be
overregulated.
um the cost burden will be excessive
and access will not be improved. Um, I
think that from everything we've seen,
40 hours of practicum is probably
excessive from what we're seeing with
our candidates and people moving through
the training programs. And I would
encourage a a less cautious and
conservative approach to this model to
try to really emphasize access and to
try to make this um more than an
afterthought when medicalization occurs
through the FDA. Thank you.
Thank you, Scott. Um, just just as a as
a note, the time frames on this actually
have come from various recommendations
through not just through some of the
committee meetings, but also in
conversations with various groups
throughout the state, including people
who have been doing this work
underground, um, and their
recommendations with regard to it. Um
and so just just so everybody knows this
is not this is not just arbitrary. This
is you know has been done with those
conversations in mind. Um and uh but we
definitely hear that as far as you know
the different requirements with regard
to you know the 40 hours for example in
some of the other states and some other
issues there. Um just to address what
Paul what you have in the chat. Um, you
know, uh, yes, there is there are also,
uh, when we get to it as far as
reciprocity, there are some factors that
are involved there, uh, as far as to
help allow for building the
infrastructure, and we'll get to that
[snorts] at that point there. Uh, and so
next we have Shane. Shane, go on ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, Shane, go ahead.
>> Okay. I'd have problems with my mic in
the past. Um, so while I appreciate
Dominic that you're talking about like
we're going to start it this way and
then if things change at, you know,
federal or whatever level in the future,
we will make adjustments as necess as
needed and and I appreciate that. But my
experience is when when a program is
started with those kind of
modalities that we're going to change in
the future, the change in the future
never happens.
Um and or become so cumbersome that it
takes forever to make those changes. Um,
while I understand that, you know, at
right now it's still schedule one at the
federal level, um, there's a bunch of
movement to change that very quickly.
Why can't we do like what Texas did with
the um I became initiative and just do
our own thing and make it right now
instead of trying to
start it this way because of one rule
knowing that you know I I'm having a
hard time explaining it I guess but I I
I just don't see that the changes will
happen the way you think that or you're
saying that they will. I think it'll be
way too cumbersome and to make those
changes and people will be resistant to
it and I I I just
I I I have low confidence that that's
going to happen correctly.
>> Thank you Shane. I appreciate that.
Okay. Uh the next step are uh mentoring
requirements.
So again
uh oh and uh I'm sorry Kate you do have
there in the chat about facilitators
working with practitioners oversightes
could it be seen as an entry point um
yes that is potentially uh you know that
is part of the idea behind it um is that
facilitators who are interested in going
for their lensure. This could be a
potential way for them to um to go in
through that process. The thing [snorts]
to remember is the statute does require
that the clinicians, which are the
diagnosing and the practitioner, do have
to have licenses in New Mexico.
Um but yes, that we do see that as a
potential way to help with that building
of additional infrastructure.
Uh so the mentoring requirements
essentially this is just what this
really just states is that the
educational programs need to provide a
methodology for mentorship after someone
has graduated and completed their
practicum. So that those uh various
providers have a place to go to consult
to talk with somebody who has experience
and to be able to do that. And so we are
saying that they the educational
programs would require 10 hours of
mentoring sessions um after the
graduation and practicums complete but
that is only valid up to 12 months. If
there are additional that is actually
worked out between the students and the
educational program.
Oh and Denali you have your hand up.
Uh, Denelli, did you if you're speaking,
we can't hear you.
>> Your mic has been enabled.
>> Oh, can you hear me now?
>> Yes, there you go. Go ahead,
>> Denali.
I I was going to say that I really um I
really value mentoring and um I'm glad
that we're anticipating it in this I I
just want to recommend that we maybe
structure it differently. Um there's a
couple of structural challenges for it
to be on the educational program. one um
you know if because we're a medical
program this mentoring is going to walk
the line with supervision and I think
it's going to be harder for programs to
make sure that they have on staff the
appropriate licensing to to do that. Um,
but I wonder if the department could
create something, you know, with their
existing permites. So, somebody who's
been a permit for um 5 years with the
department is added to a pool of mentors
and then is paired to people. This is
something the state bar does um with new
lawyers. it's a similar program um where
people are paired but I'm wondering if
it makes more sense to take from the not
not have it as a part of the education
program but within the licensing pool.
Um I appreciate that the department is
saying that it can't be added uh there
can't be an additional cost. I just I
think the reality of what the economics
the yeah folks who are trying to operate
in a training environment now and make a
living it's it's really a difficult
model and um [clears throat] I'm I'm not
really stoked about I I want it to be
accessible and I know that it's going to
be hard to ask a training program to not
charge for what is both a clinical and
supervision service. Um, [snorts] so
that's my thought on mentoring.
>> Thank you, Denelli.
Okay. Uh and the next section is
actually on recordkeeping and um
basically it is uh that all of the
programs the educational programs will
need to maintain records for their syll
sy syllabi the enrollment [snorts] for
the students um and uh and that for the
the practicums um and that they'll
provide the current and former students
their records on request and that
they'll [snorts] maintain all of the
records for five years and of course
ensure consent and confidentiality.
Okay. And then the other aspect that we
had was continuing education. Um and for
the continuing education on that we do
have that the diagnostic clinicians
complete a minimum of eight hours um
every two years that is specific to
psychedelic medicine. and then
practitioners and facilitators 20 hours
and of course keep current their uh the
life support CPR portion uh in addition
to that 20 hours that they would need to
keep that current. Um and um it it was
brought up previously that oh and I'm
apologize I pasted it into the chat but
didn't hit send. Um so my apologies on
that everyone. Um but the um these hours
because especially for people who have
lentures they are required to have other
continuing ed this is not in addition to
that. the so for example an MD who has
to do their continuing medical education
credits they just we're just asking that
they ensure that eight of those hours
are actually specific to psilocybin or
psychedelic medication um and so it's
not an additional set of continuing ed
for those individuals with lenture just
a specified area
okay any other questions questions at
this time.
Okay. So, uh please give me a moment
while I switch over to the other
document. Now, I will say on the other
document there are a couple of things
that do repeat only because we did these
in different meetings in different
sessions.
Can everybody see the document?
I'm seeing some thumbs up. So,
fantastic. Thank you everyone. So, I'll
do the same thing with regard to this.
Now, what you will see is uh again with
regard to this there are um a lot of
this uh as I mentioned has um already
been discussed. You will notice a few
highlighted areas. Those are areas that
were added um during yesterday's meeting
or are items for discussion. Um and so
this first part that I now have in and
again I'm not going to read through
every single word but just kind of go
through these are the requirements for
an educational program to become an
educational program. So what they would
have to submit to the department for the
approval process. Everything again would
be submitted through the electronic
process. Um and it would start with
organizational chart, their registration
uh with secretary of state and the tax
and rev, their certificate of occupancy.
Um and list of contact information for
owners or if a nonprofit, board of
directors, primary contact information,
which is what the department would use
and or publish for name, address, phone,
email, a list of the instructors,
including their CVs and resumes
demonstrating their expertise. Copy of
the curricula, copy of the syllabi that
will be utilized, plans for their record
retention, safety and emergency
response, transparency and disclosure of
fees for students, plans [snorts] on how
they will ensure students graduate in
two years, outline of grievance or
complaint procedures, consent for
contact information of the program to be
listed publicly, and similar for the
syllabi. And uh we do have and they'll
when we get to this part I'll talk about
it a little bit more but a third party
evaluation report um for about the
curricula and then proof of arrangements
with healing centers or other approved
location for practicum locations do
require that there must be a minimum of
two faculty with current practitioner or
facilitator permits uh by January and
that they must have experience. This was
a an add-on yesterday that they must
have experience with 40 individual
patients and the question we had was how
that could be determined or
demonstrated. Um,
so uh oh, and Chris, yes, at the very
end we'll be looking at that as far as a
vote.
any Okay, Jen Clemente.
Okay, there we go. Um, so it looks like
all of the training programs would need
to be based in New Mexico or just
because I'm I'm trying to think about
like how outofstate or online programs
would feed into this. So, Jen, we do
have a section on reciprocity and I
think you'll see that at that point.
>> Okay, great. Thanks.
>> Not a problem. It's a great question.
>> Okay, I'm not seeing others. I'll move
forward. Um and so um updates to be
provided is of course if they
essentially if the program had any
changes as far as ownership uh locations
agreements instructors they would just
need to submit that to the department
just to keep on file uh and ensure that
they're still within uh like for example
the one requirement about the two
faculty to make sure that they are
staying within that requirement. Any
questions on that?
Okay.
Uh and then uh program um curriculum
approval process. Essentially the
program would submit their application
to the department. Um and then if it's
approved it will be valid for two years.
If it's denied notice of that denial
will be sent to the program. Um, the
applicant can resubmit their application
within a six-month period, but the and
they could still do it afterwards as
well, but we want to ensure that they're
not simply resubmitting, resubmitting,
resubmitting. And so they would have a
limit that they could only submit twice
within that six-month period. Um, and
the reason for that is as we mentioned
previously and in yesterday's meeting as
well is there are no fees to submit
this. So all the application and the
review does take time for the department
and so we don't want people to quite
frankly abuse it by just saying oh we'll
submit this and but we know we don't
have all the documents please review and
let us know what else might be there. So
we don't want people to and
organizations to essentially be trying
to utilize the department as a a pre-re
so to speak. So in order to reduce that,
it could be submitted twice in that time
but not more than. Um and then of course
applicants would always have the ability
to um uh to appeal and we'll go through
that process a little bit later. It's
the same process by the way for uh
practitioners, facilitators, etc. And uh
so we'll just go through that al
together. Um and then the department
will deny an application if the
curriculum does not match the required
curricula that not all requires required
items are submitted andor if the program
instructor staff or representatives have
made false or misleading statements. Um
the review for that or renewing their
permit because it will be good for two
years. um the renewal for that is they
would have to submit it no more than 60
days and no less than 30 days prior to
the expiration of their permit. The
reason for that time frame is to ensure
one that we don't have organizations
submitting at 6 months before where they
may have changes in that 6 months time
period and the 30 days is to give the
department enough time to review it
prior to their expiration. Um, and as
with any permits or certifications of
any type, the program may voluntarily
relinquish it. They just need to let the
department know in writing.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
Uh, so this next part is the evaluation.
Um, and again, give me just a moment to
get this part in.
And this is a part where there was some
discussion yesterday and some ongoing.
And so keep that portion in mind is um
that we we have understand on this uh we
understand on this that there may be
some changes with regard to this. So we
we do get to the end of the document.
Please know that this is still in flux.
Um so uh and this was that uh the
evaluation that every program does need
to um have a third-party evaluation. One
of the things that we've talked quite a
bit about is while programs often get
approved initially, they may not have
that ongoing evaluation and that uh that
um you know looking at that to ensure
that programs are doing what they're
supposed to do. Um and so educational
programs would need to have a
third-party evaluation. Um the
department itself would is sorry
apologize everybody I've been talking a
lot for the last two days in various
meetings. Um the department may perform
remote or on-site assessments of
approved programs um with or without
prior notice. The exception for that is
during practicum and if patients are
present that must be done with notice to
ensure that it is done appropriately
with patients present. Um assessments
may include a review of the current
curriculum and they may include a review
of the record retention plan and to
ensure it is being followed and any
additional documentation uh that the
department may reasonably request to
ensure compliance with the the
requirements necessary for the
educational program. and the department
does hold the authority to withdraw
approval of a program if it is no longer
meeting the requirements.
And then the third party evaluators
portion. Um what we have here is that
third party evaluators would need to
consist of a minimum of three
individuals and those individuals would
have to have expertise in the following
areas. Psilocybin therapy practice with
a master's or doctoral degree in
counseling, therapy, social work or
related field. Medical or research
practices with M's or doctoral in
medicine, pharmacy, nursing or a related
field. And educational curriculum
development and evaluation with a
master's or doctoral degree in
education, educational psychology or a
related field. And the evaluators must
not have any conflict of interest with
the organization. And so they will have
to uh not have participated in designing
or teaching the curriculum being
evaluated and must not have a financial
interest in the organization being
evaluated. They'll have to sign a
confidentiality and impartiality
agreement and provide a report to the
both the educational program and the
department which includes at a minimum
the evaluator's experience in each of
the required fields. their conflict of
interest confidentiality agreements.
Evaluations of the reliability,
validity, and fidelity of implementation
of the curriculum. Evaluations of the
reliability, validity, and fidelity of
implementation of student evaluation and
competency, including tests, exams, and
instruction, instructor observational
feedback, and then recommendations for
approvement improvement. They'll also
need to include performance evaluations
for the faculty, an evaluation of any
reported student grievances or
complaints. The conversation that was
happening yesterday was whether or not
and if it would be possible to add a
separate path for programs that for
example have already gotten approval for
all of their curriculum with regard to
CMEs or CEUs. And so we are looking at
that. uh we would just want to ensure
that it has the rigor with having
actually evaluated the curriculum and so
that would be something that we are
looking at potentially adding in as an
alternative path.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
Uh and we had reviewed the continuing
education requirements earlier in the
other document. Um so I will skip over
that portion. Uh this next part is
uh is the reciprocity.
Um
uh and sorry there was just a comment as
I was copying that over Kate. Yes, those
can continue happening uh in further
committee meetings and also during the
rulemaking process. But again, we are
also looking at that aspect of having an
alternative path as well
to help address some of those questions
that had come up.
Okay. And so for reciprocity, what we
are looking at is individuals who've
completed training in a current
government approved psilocybin program.
We wanted to make sure this does
include, for example, any New Mexico
tribe, PBLO, Indian nation or
government. Some of the other questions
that have come up have been if it would
include uh we've talked before about
both Colorado and Oregon being included
in if they have been approved there and
that is the case, but also about other
potential programs including some that
are in Canada or in Australia. Um and we
do have a pathway for that as well. As
you'll notice, they do have to be
government approved. Um it's not
necessarily specific to US government,
just as a note there. Um those
individuals though uh would need to
complete the New Mexico module and they
would need to complete the required
practicum um that for whichever role
they are looking at um as required in
New Mexico. If some of those hours have
been completed in another jurisdiction
and they are able to be verified, then
they would just need to complete the
remaining. So the balance of those
practicum hours for the practitioner
permit, the reciprocal applicant will
need to uh ensure that they do complete
the 20 supervisory practicum hours
previously outlined. We do have
exceptions to this. Any reciprocal
application received by the department
by December 31st of 2026 would not be
required to complete the full practicum
hours, but demonstrate the completion of
at least 40 hours of contact. So a
practicum with a minimum of two separate
sessions or two separate group sessions
for preparation, administration and
integrative therapy. Um so for example
as uh has been brought up earlier in
this I think by Scott but please forgive
me if I am [snorts] incorrectly
attributing it the Colorado has 40
hours. That would be the sort of thing
that this would cover for that. Um the
other exception is that the department
reserves the ability to wave or suspend
or reduce the rules regarding the
training and practicum requirements for
individuals applying through the
reciprocal permit process in order to
facilitate the permitting of individuals
trained by other government approved
programs especially to help build the
initial infrastructure of the program.
And so this addresses some of those
concerns that have been brought up as
far as uh if we would be able to amend
things quickly. This clause actually
would allow us to be able to reduce some
of that uh without actually having to go
through additional rulemaking. But if we
put those in place permanently, we would
be able uh to then go through that rulem
process but may have them in effect
immediately.
Um and then the process for another uh
educational program to be accepted um
the applicant would need to do and
submit the following. Just document that
it has been approved by another gay
government agency. And so for example,
if they are already listed on the
department approved u list uh from
another jurisdiction, which as I've
mentioned before, we will be including
both or programs approved by Oregon and
Colorado to start. Um, if they are not
on that list, then they would just need
to provide the following documentation.
Proof that they have been approved by a
government or government entity, their
educational program curricula, and to
show a curriculum equivalency for the
dactic portion of the program when
compared to the New Mexico program. Um,
so basically a crosswalk between their
curricula and the New Mexico
requirements.
Um and then uh the programs within these
jurisdictions would be valid for two
years from the date of approval and they
of course may request a curricular
review 30 days prior to their expiration
and be renewed for two additional years.
Uh and then individuals applying for
reciprocity and having completed the
program uh outside of New Mexico will be
accepted for those practicum hours if
they apply by December 31st, 2026. And
just making sure to clarify that um
would need to actually uh demonstrate
the 40 hours as mentioned in the
previous paragraph
and Scott. Thank you. I I understand
again a lot of what we have done with
regard to this has been with consulting
with various um uh providers who have
done it including in other states and
countries and also with talking with
folks who have been doing the work um uh
prior to legalization of medical
programs.
And at this point, we'll go to hands up.
And so Ian, go ahead.
>> Hi. Um, so I know that currently, um,
the
countries outside of the US that are
working on psychedelics are mostly
English- speakaking. In the event that
that changes in the future, should we
add a requirement for like if they are
not included on the list that we should
need it translated to English and
apostled?
uh for the documentation. Um
uh that is actually a a good idea and so
we can add that on in. So thank you.
Uh Desba,
>> uh just a quick note um and it I mean it
may not even be an issue just on the the
language for the New Mexico tribe. um
just because there's the federally
recognized
um
definition and then there's also just to
point out of course um that Navajo
Nation does
mix between Arizona and New Mexico. I
don't know if there might need to be
just a little like double check to see
the language and the wording on the New
Mexico tribe governance at the
beginning.
Thank you, Despa. We actually went
through something very similar with that
regarding cannabis several years ago
with some other legislation and uh it it
um because the Navajo Nation is within
New Mexico, that was considered to be
appropriate. Um and then it's up to the
nation's own individual governance at
that point. But yeah, thank you. The
only reason, yeah, the only reason is
because I'm I don't know if someone
might say, well, New Mexico recognizes
this versus the federally recognized.
That's all.
>> Yeah. Yeah, completely understand. And
that that's the exact same situ
situation we went through several years
ago regarding cannabis. So, great
question.
Okay. Uh the next set is testing out of
the dactic portion. Um and uh for this
essentially um one of the things that
has come up quite a bit is people
talking about their um their experience
and having it having a lot of experience
and we wanted to recognize that. The
department wanted to ensure that we are
recognizing it and that came out quite a
bit in many of the committee meetings.
And so what this does is this section
really says that the educational
programs essentially need to include an
option for individuals to test out of
the didactic portion. So the classroom
portion especially if they have
experience with regard to it. We do have
a note here in order and this was in
part to help keep the costs on this down
is that the cost for someone taking just
the test cannot be more than 1/4th of
the normal price for each of the
educational modules. And of course if
they receive a passing grade then they
will have been considered to have
completed that module. And if they do
not then it will they it will be between
them and the educational program to uh
determine whether they are allowed to
retest without attending the classes.
And that's between the student and the
educational program. Um and then
students who utilize this option still
have to complete the other op the other
requirements including the certification
simulated patient and practicum
requirements to graduate.
Okay. And so the next part is the
application process. And again, uh this
is very similar to the application
process that I had mentioned earlier and
had reviewed earlier. Um so essentially
it will be online. Um and this is for
the different provider um uh
certifications and the reciprocal as
well. So it would really just be
submitting their requirements uh through
the electronic system and that they
would be valid for 2 years. Um and of
course if it is denied then a notice
provided and the same provision that we
I had mentioned earlier about they can
resubmit it again within that six-month
period but no more than twice in that
six-month period. And of course
applicants will have the ability to be
able to uh appeal if they are denied.
And again, the reasons for the
department denying an application are if
they do not show or insufficient expired
lensure, missing or inadequate
documentation,
um or if they've made false or
misleading statements. And so
essentially what this is saying is as
long as someone meets the requirements,
then they will be certified. It's only
if they do not meet those requirements
or provide them that they would not be.
And then uh the other bullets here are
the same as previous. With renewal, they
must complete the application packet
through the system uh no more than 60
days and no less than 60 or 30 days
prior to the expiration of their permit.
So the next section is uh the actual the
requirement application. So the
application itself and what would be
required on it. Um and so they would
need to demonstrate um uh their current
professional license as required for
whichever position that it is. Uh the
documentation of the appropriate
department approved training program for
that specific certification for the
provider. The documentation of the
practicum requirements. Uh documentation
of and again this is the BLS or um CPR
certification. Um that part is not
needed for the diagnostic clinician.
Document of current HIPPA certification
at testation. They are not a registered
sex offender or they will be denied. Uh
and personal data data as appropriate.
So date of birth, driver's license or
state ID, phone, email address, legal
name and affiliation. Uh I'm sorry and
affirmation and consent forms.
And then for the reciprocal this is uh
very similar
uh this is very similar with regard to
uh the previous one. So they complete
their documentation and then they would
have to provide if it's a a program that
is not currently on the list for recip
reciprocal educational programs, they
would need to or they could provide that
documentation. And so then uh
essentially that [snorts] program from
another state or jurisdiction added to
the list of department approved if they
meet the requirements. Um and then they
would have to uh document their um their
active practitioner or facilitator
equivalent lensure or permit in another
jurisdiction. Document that they have
completed the uh practicum hours. Um and
then documentation of the New Mexico
specific module. Uh verification of the
[snorts] BLS CPR certification, HIPPA
certification, W9, and I'll mention why
we need that in a moment. and then at
test station again they are not a
registered sex offender and then the
appropriate personal data. Um some
people had asked previously why we had
asked for a W9. The reason for that is
because when we do have uh the equity
and access fund up and running uh as far
as for reimbursements for it that will
most likely be through the providers
themselves that they'll get reimbursed.
And to do so it has to go through the
state financial system which is called
the share system. And for us to do that,
we would need the W9. So we have added
that in here in that application. So we
have that right off the bat and are able
to get individuals registered so they do
not have a delay later on if they are
looking at utilizing that fund for some
of their patients. Um and then Alana
>> uh just this attestation um a few
questions. one is like why an att
testation verse linking to some of our
data sources because like I mean we've
collected that information.
>> Um and then second like what about like
other criminal ca charges or like
convictions of fraud? There might be
other things that we might want to know
about a provider's background.
>> Yeah. So it's a great question Alana. we
are able to do that with regard to the
sex offender aspect and we would be
verifying that and looking that on up.
Um we just wanted to ensure that we have
that as attestation and to be very clear
we are doing that. As far as for
background checks, the department does
not actually have authority to require
those um for the complete ones and so
that is not something that we are doing
at this time. But that is one thing that
with the licensing boards, the majority
of licensing boards that I know of do
require that. And so we also feel pretty
confident with regard to that for the
licensing side for those individuals who
are licensed that they already will have
that background check. That's a great
question, but uh yeah, uh I hope that
answers why. [laughter]
Uh Ian,
>> actually I was going to say something on
a similar vein to Alana. um on at least
for most healthcare providers, they have
to get a a HCA background check and that
will say like um if they've abused
patients or it'll it'll tell a lot more
information than an attistation. So, I
was just similarly curious if it was
better to maybe see if we could do
anything with the HCA or maybe find
another agency that could do a more full
background check because these are very
vulnerable patients when they are um
going on a journey.
>> Thank you. I Denali.
>> Hi. Uh, it sounds like this maybe is
just covered through um whatever is
required through individual licenses,
but I I'm just going to recommend that
if the department does create any
prohibitions of certain convictions that
it includes also an opportunity to
provide rehabilitative evidence. you
know, this is a program that's based on
healing and um I think we should
recognize that um providers also
experience that transformation. So,
>> thank you, Denal. Uh and Larry.
>> Oh, Larry, you're still muted.
>> Under um storage says all psilocybin
products stored in approved location
must be kept within a locked area. Is
there some place where we're specifying
how much psilocybin um can be stored? I
know that there's been different
regulations in different states.
>> So, Larry, we haven't gotten to that
part yet, but short answer is uh no.
>> Okay. And the um the other I just want
to point something out about the um
reciprocity and the and the practicum
and um as you heard me say before, I I I
love people being more trained, but I'm
also concerned about the numbers. it. So
if we give reciprocity to people from
Colorado, they may have done um
basically uh two clients, both of who
are well um and their own session and
it's when they train here, they're going
to be required for a lot more. So I'm
just it's almost like we're giving some
encouragement for people to get trained
in Colorado during reciprocity.
>> Thank you, Larry. Um and that's actually
why that has a a sunset clause of uh de
the end of December. We understand that
uh you know we are lucky enough to have
other states that actually already have
programs and so we're able to actually
utilize that somewhat. If we were
starting this with no other states
having that there would be a definite
time period even though we'd be saying
here's when it starts there would be a
definite lag time before there even
would be able to be providers and
patients. So this does help us as far as
uh having some of that re those
resources from other places that we can
also help or rely upon. Um but that's
why that portion does have a sunset
clause where those individuals would
have to apply by those dates by the end
of December um in order to um have that
aspect because the other part on the
practicum is if they go through the
training somewhere else they still would
need to complete the New Mexico
practicum hours.
after that after the sunset date.
>> Thank you, Dom.
>> Uh Alana.
>> Yeah, I just I'm just going to go back
to that one more time. Amy, it sounds
like it's a little bit outside of the
scope or purview of DO um and
potentially out of the statute. I just
do want to call that I think it is a gap
and an area of potential risk for
patients that there isn't more robust
oversight over safety in this particular
like background check situation. Um like
the process for becoming an enrolled
provider is much much more robust than
licensing. Uh and so
I think it I think it's a gap. I think
and I guess that I would just also point
out that if people like the billing will
they'll have to adhere to the
requirements of what you know commercial
and Medicaid and Medicare to bill. I
don't know about Medicare but Medicaid
and commercial to bill. Um so and just
we have had problems with that with
providers who expect that the DOH rules
will apply to them and supersede their
requirements for Medicaid. And so just
to to be reimbursed for the services,
they'll have to follow all of the um
like
provider validation and certification
requirements. Um like I am a little bit
nervous there isn't a background check
of any type for providers who are going
to be with these v vulnerable patients.
Um so just when I guess I'll point that
out, but if if there isn't like a a meth
a mechanism then then that's that.
Right. Thank you. Thank Thank you,
Alana. And yes, that is I agree that is
a gap. It is just not something that we
can actually do without that specific
statutory requirement. Um so yes and and
it is a part uh and it's one of the
things that within the documentation it
will actually be uh outlined and
described that regardless of whether
someone is meeting the do requirements
on this for billing purposes they'll
still need to meet those requirements
for Medicaid and for insurers. [snorts]
Okay. [snorts] Uh and so the next aspect
is actually the uh patient application
um and record.
Uh and with this um you know it it again
the applicant um and this really is done
with a diagnosing clinician and this is
a very similar process to what we have
uh for many of our current programs. Um
and essentially it will include a
documentation of the diagnosis of the
qualifying commi condition by the um
diagnosing clinician. It'll have the
personal data um and uh and then the
diagnosing clinician, the practitioners
and the facilitators will need to
utilize it simply to do the tracking to
record the information about the
diagnosis of the qualifying patient,
their attestations about evaluating and
treating the patient. um date and time
for services for various evaluations,
prep sessions, administration day, and
the um integrative therapy sessions.
Also includes for uh reporting for any
adverse events or complaints and then
information of course as those rules get
fleshed out uh for the equity and access
fund.
Okay. And then the next part is
um
uh the application appeal process and
disciplinary actions.
And we're almost
through. Um just give me a little bit
more. Um
Uh thank you Sky for the comment in
there as far as uh for uh non-English
speakers. Um and again as far as for
that that is really um you know uh
programs are going to need to be able to
have both English and Spanish. So thank
you very much on that. Um and then there
are requirements with ADA and language
uh I forget what the name of the act is
but something like language access act
or something like that that requires
translations for uh for individuals who
are non-English speakers as well.
Um so application appeal process
essentially what this just says is that
if an application is denied for any
reason that there would be an
administrative review process. Um and
this is actually the same process that
occurs current in the the regulations
that I mentioned earlier for production
and laboratory. So there would be an
administrative review of the application
and then a final determination
um that would happen on that. And then
the other aspect are disciplinary
actions that if there is something where
uh someone who has a certification or
permit has done um has for example in
the areas where they have been um uh
misleading or mistruthful then they the
or if they have done something that put
someone in harm's way or safety issues
or not meeting any of the regulations
the department can issue a notice of
disciplinary action. they would have the
ability to uh remediate that. They can
also then request um a hearing within 30
calendar days and the hearing will be no
later than 60 days from the request. It
is overseen by a hearing officer. They
can grant continuences as needed. Um and
I notice there is a typo there. Fix
that. uh hearing officer shall submit a
written recommendation within 30 days
and then issue a final written decision
within 45 calendar days.
Okay. And then the next section is on
the healing centers.
And so uh and again with this this is
really just the locations for where the
administration would be taking place.
And again what their recommendations are
is very similar to all of the others
that we have required their business
license those sort of items. Plans for
record retention and confidentiality
secure storage wastage of any unused
medication. Um and that's just in the
event event for example someone uh is
given like a cup of tea they only
consume half of it or they are given
pills or capsules they're handling them
consume only some of them and then the
others need to be disposed of. Uh safety
and emergency response plans
demonstrations
uh on their policies for confidentiality
um and plans for transparency and
disclosure of fees. outline of complaint
and grievance processes. Um consent for
contact information and websites to be
publicly listed if approved. Um and then
uh and we'd noted earlier from your
comment Chris uh and from Larry as far
as uh making sure that that's a we're
talking about remote areas, not
someone's backyard situation, but for a
natural environments about having
permission to utilize the property. a
description of the administration area
including safe entrances and exits and
verification it's free of hazards,
emergency safety response plan. And then
um the two individuals present and again
for remote areas uh who are not
receiving treatment to have either first
aid certification or wilderness first
respond responder and again have that
plan for adverse health event response
and reporting.
And then the other item uh was other
approved locations. So this would be for
those situations for example when
someone is uh not able to either
physically leave their home or location
due to medical necessity. Also for areas
where uh with regard to having a mobile
unit for rural areas. So this would be
approval of temporary or locations or a
patient's residence and would
essentially follow similar process but
less requirements. So you don't need to
have the business license, all of that
sort of information, but a list of the
permitted individuals utilizing the
location, secure transportation, and if
necessary, storage for medication, plans
for wastage of any unused, safety and
emergency plan. A plan for storage of
firearms or other weapons safely during
and after treatment sessions, plans
demonstrating confidentiality of
patients will be maintained, and then a
description of why the location is
appropriate for treatment sessions.
Uh and then the responsibilities
on this
um they would be required to uh only
psilocybin products may be consumed in
an approved location. only patients and
certified individuals present during the
treatment unless the patient gives
written prior consent for other
individuals except of course emergency
response situations. Um, and by the way,
we uh the question came up yesterday
about other staff who may be there who
don't have the certification or the
permits. And uh the answer on that is
that should be a part of the consent
form for during the treatment that those
staff members may be coming on in. But
we will clarify that here as well as far
as for the rules. Um and then uh the
permittee um uh must maintain a copy of
the daily logs related to psilocybin and
they may not promote unregulated
cultivation and processing uh and may
not sell unregulated products. Provide
required information to the department
upon request and they must display of
cop of course a copy of the healing
center certification and information
regarding safe transport after an
administration session. We did also have
the request to add in the patient bill
of rights and so um I also have that
here as well.
Uh Hanifea,
hi thank you so much for a great
meeting. I've been listening uh
diligently and just have a few couple
questions and a few comments. One is
that um still not hearing and I'm not
clear on how the medicine is being
transported and the rules and reporting
around that. Um I don't know if I missed
it but in the New Mexico module is there
a section on reporting and training
people on you know how to report etc.
Will there be uh will there will there
be reporting on patient
recorded out reported outcomes as well
as the equity and um you know uh
incidents of safety that might come up.
I'm curious how we're going to be
tracking the outcomes the patient
reported outcomes. And then the last
thing I'll just say, um, as a fan of
congruency, I think that the diagnosing
clinician title is just inconsistent
with the role of that person. And I
would recommend a name of elig
eligibility clinician because they're
going to be diagnosing potentially
approving or confirming a diagnosis and
doing the medical and safety screening.
So just in this period of congruency, I
would recommend that. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Heneifeha. Um the
transportation actually was in the
previous rule on the produ producers and
laboratories. So that portion is in
there. Um and um uh so that part is
there. Um yeah.
So we do we are almost at the very end
of this. Um there's just a little bit
more with regard to this. So, um, you
know, I'd like to go ahead and show that
and then we can see what, um, what the
board thinks at that time. Um, so the
next sections, and I'm going to just put
this all in together because I think
it's pretty much mostly um,
administrative for the most part. Um but
that essentially that each of the
locations does have to have a safety
plan. Documenting their procedures for
emergency response and uh things like
disruptive com uh conduct um ensuring
that there are um practitioners and
facilitators present at all time and
ensuring that they provide the emergency
and safety plan to all individuals. Um,
and then from a storage, and this is the
question Larry had earlier, is that they
just need to be stored in a uh in a
protected area. So, a place enclosed
with permanent walls and a a steel grade
door with a non-residential lock or a
locked safe and products that require
refrigeration in a locked refrigerator
or freezer. Um and then the adverse
health event reporting is uh that if
there are any potential adverse health
events that they actually need to be
reported within 2 days um regarding that
and that healing centers must maintain
records of those uh events and they must
include the patient record number, the
product ID that was utilized,
participants reaction requiring medical
attention, any incidents requiring
emergency response and negative in uh uh
impact on a patient. Um and then
complaint reporting uh again similar it
just needs to be reported and launched
the complaint with the department um and
that it should include of course the
name of the person complaining the
nature of the complaint and uh that the
additional re information may be
requested for investigational purposes.
And then the last little bit is that uh
the healing centers and approved
locations must take adequate measures to
make the instructions or guidance
available for how to file those
complaints with uh the department or
other relevant state entities and the
process on how to report an adverse
health event. And so with that we are at
the end of the document.
Ian,
>> hey, I just wanted to say I think this
is a great document. It clearly
emphasizes patient safety and um just
general well-being throughout it. The
education materials are all relevant to
the positions and um establish a good
baseline for what they need to know
without, you know, going too much into
the weeds. So, I just thank you for the
document.
>> Thank you.
So at this point we do and we understand
from the department standpoint that
there are considerations regarding uh
the concerns that we've pointed out and
discussed throughout this. Um but at
this time we're we would like to start
moving forward with some of the
rulemaking and again with the
understanding that there are additional
committee meetings. There are uh other
items um for example the concern as far
as CS numbers uh the amount of practicum
hours for consideration and continued
discussion. But at this point we'd like
to move forward with the essential basic
framework.
Oh, and just to answer a question, Jen,
um the there's no limit on that.
>> Hey, Desped
Kate Hawk's comment earlier up in the
about the home facilities, especially
for um end of life care.
Um yeah and again that is that's covered
under the other locations where they can
apply for that.
Oh, and Sky, we are not requiring
cameras because the there are people who
um you know may be going through
treatment and do not necessarily want
their sessions recorded, but that will
be up to the healing centers themselves.
Larry,
>> yeah, thanks Tom. Um, I I'm responding
to to Chris's to Chris's comment, you
know, about um um needing more time to
discuss this to for him to be willing to
support it. And I I'm also honestly, you
know, I I came back from leave and I had
a whole email full of people in the
community that are concerned. Um I just
wanted to clarify um if we do approve
the basic structure here, is there
anything that can't be changed at a more
spacious conversation at the next
meeting? I think that's that would
address Chris's concerns and maybe
others.
>> We have a couple other comments. So,
we'll go forward with those first and
then I'll see if I can't answer. Despa,
go ahead.
>> Yeah, sorry. I just kind of also wanted
to point that out just really quickly.
you know where I understand that we're
trying to not trying we are very
concerned with um you know how we are
providing
you know the regulations you know New
Mexico first our New Mexico people and
really understanding that this has to be
based you know for us for ourselves
um to kind of make sure that we also
realize that you know there are barriers
even for Um,
let's just I always point to myself, you
know, it's when I was coming from
Massachusetts, the requirements for me
to have the reciprocity as a massage
therapist, you know, those barriers are
for, you know, putting a face to, I
guess, that kind of thing. um as a
single parent, you know, we don't know
where um that lies in terms of
the the types of individuals that are
coming into here and a lot of the people
that are that can do the the
facilitation or maybe, you know, that's
part of the thing is we're more on the
reciprocity of time and energy versus
the amount of dollars and financial
burdens that it might require. Not just
that, but um you know, I don't know. I
just I'm kind of sort of echoing with
what Chris is saying, those kinds of
concerns. I know that we need to have
people heart first um taking care of
individuals here in New Mexico, but
really understanding that a lot of the
work that we have done in the healing
space is is is is just from the
generosity of our own heart and it's not
for financial gain. And then so where
are we going to be able to have that
financial ability and the time to be
able to um catch up to those
requirements? And that's kind of where I
feel like maybe some of us are coming
from. And I just kind of wanted to say
that. So that's all.
>> Thank you, Desba. Uh Senator Steinborn.
>> Thanks. Good morning, Dominic, and
everybody. Great work today. I mean,
this is the serious substance. I uh it
sounds like there's consensus on most of
the of the items. Um I know there's a
lot of heartburn with an item or two and
I'm wondering if it's possible that
maybe those areas there could be more
discussion on not today but um have a
have a special meeting. maybe providers
I'm starting to get here and I don't
know if that's their concern but but
maybe warrants a little more in-depth
discussion on an item or two and then
kind of move forward on everything else
while we try to just kind of flesh out
those other ones.
>> Thank you, Senator. And I I definitely
appreciate it and that actually fits in
with what Larry was asking and that's
part of why I was saying you know we
seem to have that with regard to the
majority of it and there are those
couple areas where additional you know
conversations and considerations need to
be and so we're not asking that that be
shut down at this point. We're just
saying you know to continue to move
forward as well as continuing to have
those conversations
>> for sure. Thank you. great work on
everything. I know it's a lot of work.
Appreciate it.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> Thank you, sir. Uh Ian.
>> Yeah. So, um I just kind of wanted to
address some of Desbos's concerns
because I do believe that is a very real
issue that we experience in the world.
And I don't have experience with a
professional degree, but I do know how
annoying it is uh trying to get medical
cannabis reciprocity and of much of the
United States. Um minus New Mexico, but
I'm a domestic patient here. So, um I
just wanted to look at that, but I
wanted to kind of emphasize for her that
um we would accept any governmental
entity. So, if it was Massachusetts, if
they had a program, Oregon, Colorado,
Canada, Australia, whatever
association of people have created
themselves to govern, um that is would
be accepted is what I'm hearing. So, we
wouldn't have the same problems as
having to review each state. Um well we
would review each state but we have a
internalized list of saying if they have
experience if they have um the education
then we can accept it just as much as we
could if we offered it here. Um I do
think in terms of time we might just um
move the practitioner I mean the
diagnostic clinician to another day and
then vote on the rest of the packet cuz
I feel like there's a lot of consensus.
Um, if I'm wrong, please correct me,
anyone in the board. But, um, I feel
like most of this document is a slam
dunk. Even most of the practitioner part
minus the that controlled substance
would probably need more discussion.
Well, and that's why what I'm really
asking is that with that understanding
that we have those continued discussions
regarding the diagnostic clinician with
regard to the controlled substance
number, uh the some of the practicum
requirements. Um and I do see in the
chat that there's some concerns as far
as some of the reciprocity for the
timeline uh that could actually be
extended potentially as well, but that
we have that we continue those
discussions um at this point. but
continue to move forward as far as
starting to craft the regulatory side.
>> Yeah. So, I would say take a motion on
that and get that voted on because we
are barely at a quorum at this point.
>> We have Brenda.
Uh yeah, I just want to um go over a
couple of things and and yes, uh let's I
want to propose that we discuss this in
the next training and education and put
a pin in some of these things. Uh so it
could be discussed further. Uh but for
now, uh voting on these uh some of these
iteings right now, they look like
they're really good to go. uh especially
for things like practicum. And also too,
I wanted to note that maybe have
something for a pro bono um item too for
some of uh practitioners that may want
to also provide that uh free of charge
for um some of the patients because uh
this program is just starting out and
maybe some of the people in practicum
will need that. Uh so um I want to just
propose that and maybe just put a pin in
some of these other items and to be
discussed further. Um you know again
like the practicum hours uh from what
we're hearing that other other people
are saying that you know 40 hours could
be too much and yes the timeline to try
to fit in the practicum hours especially
for reciprocity could um uh kind of uh
put a lot of pressure on a lot of
clinicians. So I just wanted to note
that.
>> Thank you, Brenda. Ian.
>> All right. So then I will propose the
formal motion. Um I move to adopt these
recommendations minus the practicum
requirement um the controlled substance
number requirement and uh the reciprocal
timeline. If you are in favor of this
document minus those three things, if
you could please raise your hand at this
time.
All right, we have two in favor. If you
could lower your Oh, three in favor. Or
are you no or yes, Larry?
>> You're muted, by the way.
I'm reflecting. Yes, I'd prefer to have
more discussion honestly, but I I I
can't accept this.
>> Okay, perfect.
>> We have three. And then if you could
lower your hands.
>> All right. And then if you are opposed,
please raise your hand.
And then you may lower it. Oh, two.
All righty. The vote is three in favor,
two against. Again, we have adopted this
minus the practicum controlled substance
number and um reciprocity timeline which
will be discussed at the next meeting.
When is everyone free for their next
meeting?
>> Um I'm sorry, this is Larry. I just want
to also say something because I feel
like I did make a little bit of a
deciding vote. My understanding is that
we can still have discussion on these
topics. It's not closed off in the
future because I think we don't have
consensus on some of the other things.
And I just want to speak that that I'm
voting in favor, but I also favor more
discussion. I saw Dom nodding, which I
appreciate.
>> Yeah. Yes, that that is correct, Larry.
>> Perfect. All righty. Well, thank you for
um explaining your vote. And then when
is
everyone free for the next meeting?
>> We're looking at July, right? Or
>> I would say so.
>> Okay. [laughter]
Just trying not to make sure I jump
ahead too far ahead.
>> So my guess is um is the department
closed the third, right? for observance
of 4th of July or no?
>> We uh the department is closed on the
3rd and the 10th already has several
other meetings uh for some of the
committees um that are set up. Um uh
however the 17th would be open in the
morning.
>> All righty. Um,
does the department need these
resolutions
now or would you like us by the 17th or
would you like us to push them out now
or earlier uh meeting
to at least discuss them?
Are you saying that we maybe should
discuss them on the 17th verse? I or are
you propo? Sorry. And are you proposing
to try to discuss them prior to meeting
to
>> I'm trying to see if items.
>> So I'm trying to see the date we should
discuss the remaining items. So okay, we
could meet on the 17th. That's the next
Friday that's available.
>> Um
>> or we could do it before. There's just
it would have to be on a different day
is what I was trying to say.
>> I think for
>> do a different day if we're going to
meet again as like a group, but I'm also
I'm fine with having a discussion on the
17th, but I pref I think we should have
a discussion prior to the 17th.
>> Uh is the the ETH doesn't have any
meetings, right?
>> Uh the ETH would be open. Okay. Okay. Uh
I have a meeting that I need to change,
but um I think that person is actually
on this meeting as well. And so uh if
the ETH is, we'll see about changing
that.
>> And then uh Brenda,
>> I can't make the ETH just to show that.
>> Yes, same.
>> In the afternoon. Yeah, I'm willing to
um open my uh the education training
meeting to discuss these um topics uh so
we can uh do it in in my meeting on uh
the 17th from 1 to 3, but if we're if
we're going to do it on the 17th in the
morning. So I I just wanted to leave
that open for more discussion and and
possible other topics as well.
Um,
so Thursday the 9th,
>> that works for me.
>> Uh, between 9 and 11.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah,
>> I can make that work, too.
>> Perfect. Perfect.
>> And Larry and then Brenda.
Uh, I think I can make it work. I could
just um move some clients around in the
morning.
>> If you're okay with that, that would be
great. Um,
>> yeah. Yeah, sure. Sure. I mean, yeah, I
can do it. I can do it.
>> Perfect. Well, thank you guys so much
for coming and for your discussions
today and everyone in the um public that
has brought information to us. We really
appreciate you being here today with us
um and spending your morning with us.
Happy Friday, everyone. I hope you have
a wonderful weekend. Um, I will go ahead
and adjoin this meeting. We'll be
meeting next at July 9th at 9:00 a.m.
>> And thank you everybody. Really do
appreciate all of this work and the
feedback. You know, again, we have to
start somewhere and so this is a
wonderful start and I look forward to
the continued discussion. Have a great
weekend.